<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-07-10T19:06:46+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/</id><title type="html">Social Tech Playbook</title><subtitle>The Social Tech Playbook for COVID-19 Response is a technology guide for social service agencies responding to the increased demand for basic needs during the coronavirus pandemic.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">More plays coming soon!</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/more-coming-soon/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="More plays coming soon!" /><published>2020-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/more-coming-soon</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/more-coming-soon/">&lt;p&gt;More coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">More coming soon!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">More plays coming soon!</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/another-one/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="More plays coming soon!" /><published>2020-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/another-one</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/another-one/">&lt;p&gt;More coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">More coming soon!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Make policy changes that improve service delivery</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/contactless-policy-changes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Make policy changes that improve service delivery" /><published>2020-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/contactless-policy-changes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/contactless-policy-changes/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;This play was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alluma.org&quot;&gt;Alluma&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.civilla.com&quot;&gt;Civilla&lt;/a&gt;, partners in the Social Tech Collaborative.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although changes to program rules often require federal authorization through a waiver or state plan amendment, agencies and CBOs have autonomy to make other policy changes that will have an immediate impact on their staff and families in need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helping staff simplify existing workflows and improve service delivery through revisions to existing policies and procedures are changes that any government or non-profit can enact without external approval. Often these are small changes that can have a big impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months and years of recovery ahead, changes to policy and procedures made during the current crisis will likely need to continue long-term – with ongoing adjustments – in order to meet a continuing demand for services. Anticipating client and staff needs now will help to respond to changes in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices-for-this-play&quot;&gt;Best practices for this play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-can-be-done-quickly&quot;&gt;What can be done quickly&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improve contactless interactions with individuals &amp;amp; families&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implement policies to limit and redesign in-person interactions between:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Staff and staff&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Staff and applicants/beneficiaries&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Applicants/beneficiaries to each other (e.g., office lobbies)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adopt policies that reduce the need for paper verifications
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Increase use of electronic data sources&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Allow self-attestation&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Encourage greater use of collateral contacts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Re-use verifications for multiple criteria (e.g., use paycheck stubs as proof of income as well as residency).&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shift enrollment processes to focus on no or low touch approaches
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Identify all client - agency interactions that were previously only available in-person&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Determine alternative avenues for service delivery (online, phone, fax, etc). If a task can only be done in-person, consider removing the requirement altogether (at least temporarily).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use digital channels to communicate (text messaging, email, phone, etc). Communicate with clients more frequently to reassure and provide updates so they do not feel the need to see someone in-person.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Empower staff to use their discretion to approve cases, not deny applicants&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Conduct interviews on the same day an application is submitted&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a simplified intake form&lt;/strong&gt; that can be used for multiple programs so applicants only need to provide information one time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow for more opt-out rather than opt-in options&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Example: If an applicant provides a mobile phone #, opt them in for text messages and provide an easy option to opt-out or ask for their consent by replying to the initial message.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revise consent language so applicants can agree to have their information shared if doing so would be beneficial to them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Review and revise policies that are unnecessary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Example: Requiring applicants to authenticate their identity before an intake form or application can be entered into the system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re-evaluate measurements for success&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Revise performance measures to focus on outcomes such as:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reduced application processing times&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reduced # of touchpoints needed&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reduced # of procedural denials&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Reduced % of churn&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Accept a temporary increase in error rates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increase over-issuance amount&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Postpone quality control, audits, or routine maintenance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyze call center/web data to help reduce call volume
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Review common questions or search terms to determine what information callers are seeking. Use that information to streamline operations, improve communications, etc&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Review where people fall off in the process and simplify the user experience&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Review usage patterns (ex: high/low volume of callers) to adjust staffing and resource availability&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-to-aim-for-long-term&quot;&gt;What to aim for long term&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep momentum by setting new standards and upending old paradigms
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Do not assume you can or must return to pre-crisis processes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Challenge all policy or operating assumptions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a dedicated, multi-disciplinary team to focus long-term on re-designing and improving service delivery from end to end.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Conduct an in-depth review of operating costs before and after policy or operations changes to document outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simplify policy and legal language in operations manual, notices, forms using plain language.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue expanding self-service options for beneficiaries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue to identify specific tasks or steps in a process that can be automated or eliminated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/codeforamerica-cms1/documents/COVID-19-SNAP-Policy-Delivery-Memo.pdf&quot;&gt;COVID-19 SNAP Policy + Delivery Memo&lt;/a&gt;, Code for America, April 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bdtrust.org/Brief-Remote_Application_Assistance_for_SNAP_During_COVID-19.pdf&quot;&gt;Facilitating Remote Application Assistance for SNAP During COVID-19: Recommendations for States and Application Assisters&lt;/a&gt;, Benefits Data Trust, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nascio.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/NASCIO_ChatbotsRespondtoCOVID-19.pdf&quot;&gt;Chatbots respond to COVID-19&lt;/a&gt; (NASCIO)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://statescoop.com/nearly-75-percent-states-launched-chatbots-aid-pandemic-response/&quot;&gt;Nearly 75% of states launched chatbots to aid pandemic response&lt;/a&gt; (StateScoop)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/codeforamerica-cms1/documents/delivery-driven-policy-code-for-america.pdf&quot;&gt;Delivery-Driven Policy&lt;/a&gt;, Code for America, September 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alluma Checklists
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alluma.org/sites/default/files/2020-06/Alluma_Functions_Checklist.pdf&quot;&gt;The Tech-Savvy Checklist for Benefit Agencies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alluma.org/sites/default/files/2020-06/Alluma_Key_Features.pdf&quot;&gt;The Key Features of a Successful Portal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This play was written by Alluma and Civilla, partners in the Social Tech Collaborative.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lead change and remote work in a time of crisis</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/change-management-in-a-time-of-crisis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lead change and remote work in a time of crisis" /><published>2020-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/change-management-in-a-time-of-crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/change-management-in-a-time-of-crisis/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;This play was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alluma.org&quot;&gt;Alluma&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.civilla.com&quot;&gt;Civilla&lt;/a&gt;, partners in the Social Tech Collaborative.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amid the COVID-19 pandemic, social services organizations around the country have pivoted to remote work. It’s remarkable to see how fast organizations have been able to adapt their service delivery models in a short period of time. But the transition has also been challenging. To be able to respond to the changes in business processes required in this current crisis, leaders must find new ways to help their teams adopt remote work practices and creatively problem solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the months and years of recovery ahead, it is unlikely that daily operations for benefit delivery will return to how they were done pre-pandemic. To be successful in the long term, social service organizations will need to continue investing the time, intention, and resources that are needed to make remote work a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices-for-this-play&quot;&gt;Best practices for this play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-can-be-done-quickly&quot;&gt;What can be done quickly&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Establish an effective remote work environment for staff&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify and prioritize new infrastructure/IT needs.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ensure staff computers have an up-to-date operating system, browser, and antivirus software&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Set up infrastructure for communications, such as conference calls, videoconferencing, and a Virtual Private Network (VPN)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Agree on a file-sharing method for remote work that includes version control and accounts for relevant security concerns&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide basic instructions and training&lt;/strong&gt; to remote staff on all new IT systems or processes. Do not assume they will be able to “just figure it out.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Establish an IT help line for staff&lt;/strong&gt; that is supported by “super users” who can help colleagues navigate the new processes or infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update and re-issue security and confidentiality policies.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Determine what information needs to be encrypted and how it should be sent by remote staff&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Remind remote staff to talk with clients by phone or video in a location where there is privacy&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Ensure physical records are stored in a secure place&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Remind staff to either delete personal information from shared mobile devices (including tablets) and/or to enable necessary security features&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Find alternative ways to answer questions&lt;/strong&gt; or provide feedback to team members.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For example, supervisors can provide “office hours” or answer questions through a dedicated IM channel where everyone can post and see answers.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Designate a shared document or folder or intranet to be the “single source of truth”&lt;/strong&gt; for changes, decisions, goals and priorities, and other “need to know” information. It is more difficult to keep track of key information or actions needed with multiple communication channels.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talk to staff about how to build a strong team culture&lt;/strong&gt; without interacting face-to-face at the office.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Explicitly ask team members about their obligations and preferred schedules when working remotely&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Virtually share calendars with all team members to facilitate remote work&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Provide collaboration and communication tools that can be used for informal and formal conversations (in addition to e-mail)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Schedule time in standing meetings for check-ins and less-structured conversations&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Re-evaluate goals&lt;/strong&gt; and the need for standing meetings
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Limit meeting participation to only those critical for decision making (vs. informational)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shorten length of meetings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clearly identify what actions/decisions are needed by end of the meeting&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consistently communicate actions/decisions to all stakeholders to ensure information is timely and accurate.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create standardized templates&lt;/strong&gt; for case notes to help reduce time needed for workers to input the needed information.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Example: Nevada Human Services Agency created a standard template for its case workers to help them indicate cases if a case was being processed under COVID-19 waivers as required by state and federal policy. The template helped ensure consistency in the case files while making compliance with the new rules easier and quicker.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prepare scripts, FAQs, and “cheat sheets”&lt;/strong&gt; to help staff answer common questions from individuals or families. Update materials frequently so staff stay up-to-date on policy or process changes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empower staff and decentralize certain decision making.&lt;/strong&gt; Reward/incentivize creative ideas to improve the status quo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managing remote staff in crisis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a rapid response team
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Establish and clearly communicate the process for escalating issues&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Remove hierarchical barriers to allow more open communication and feedback&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hold short “stand-up” meetings daily&lt;/strong&gt; with key staff to identify priorities and roadblocks for the day or week. Check-in frequently with front-line staff (including those working remotely) to understand roadblocks and celebrate successes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use real-time data&lt;/strong&gt; to better understand operations. Review data regularly to see if changes to policies or processes have the intended outcomes or if adjustments are still needed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share results in real-time&lt;/strong&gt; so all staff are aligned on priorities and desired outcomes.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Example: Create a dashboard for tracking progress that can be shared with staff and upper management.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Consider non-traditional staffing arrangements&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Schedule shifts for backend processing times before and after working hours (to decrease demand on systems during peak hours)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Temporarily reassign staff from other departments or areas to help increase staffing for critical functions (e.g., call center, data entry)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-to-aim-for-long-term&quot;&gt;What to aim for long term&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Establish a clear process for new ideas&lt;/strong&gt; to be shared, evaluated, and implemented quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use new staff, processes, and policies&lt;/strong&gt; that were put in place during the crisis for long-term changes.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Example: Re-purpose the temporary rapid response team to a dedicated problem-solving team tasked with long-term improvements&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implement and maintain new approaches&lt;/strong&gt; to management, collaboration, and culture, especially for staff who continue to work remotely.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create or update crisis-response plans&lt;/strong&gt; and capabilities based on lessons learned.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Develop staffing plans&lt;/strong&gt; needed with reduced budgets, increased volume, and more automation.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Example: Conduct a gap analysis of future technical/skilled job functions needed and existing staff’s skills to plan for upskilling programs&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Webinar: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UtLSb1qfWEs&quot;&gt;Successful Remote and Distributed Work in Uncertain Times,&lt;/a&gt; Code for America, March 12, 2020&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mckinsey.com/featured-insights/coronavirus-leading-through-the-crisis/navigating-to-the-next-normal-the-first-100-insights&quot;&gt;Navigating to the next normal: The first 100 insights,&lt;/a&gt; McKinsey Consulting, Spring 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;City of Los Angeles Portal for Remote Staff - &lt;a href=&quot;https://connect2lacity.org/&quot;&gt;https://connect2lacity.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gomb.utah.gov/a-new-workplace-modernizing-where-how-and-when-utah-works/&quot;&gt;A New Workplace: Modernizing Where, How, And When Utah Works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://oshr.nc.gov/policies-forms/employment-records/teleworking-program-policy&quot;&gt;North Carolina Teleworking Program Policy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://statescoop.com/how-los-angeles-suddenly-moved-10000-workers-online/&quot;&gt;https://statescoop.com/how-los-angeles-suddenly-moved-10000-workers-online/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.routefifty.com/management/2020/03/local-governments-still-open-telework/164141/&quot;&gt;Local Government’s Still Open—Remotely&lt;/a&gt;, Route Fifty, March 26, 2020&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://statescoop.com/list/12-takeaways-from-cios-on-the-rapid-move-to-remote-work/&quot;&gt;https://statescoop.com/list/12-takeaways-from-cios-on-the-rapid-move-to-remote-work/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This play was written by Alluma and Civilla, partners in the Social Tech Collaborative.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Target outreach to individuals applying for unemployment compensation</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/target-outreach-to-individuals-applying-for-unemployment-compensation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Target outreach to individuals applying for unemployment compensation" /><published>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/target-outreach-to-individuals-applying-for%20unemployment-compensation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/target-outreach-to-individuals-applying-for-unemployment-compensation/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;This play was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://bdtrust.org/&quot;&gt;Benefits Data Trust&lt;/a&gt;, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 40 million people filed for unemployment benefits between mid-March and late May – the equivalent of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/05/28/business/economy/coronavirus-unemployment-claims.html&quot;&gt;one out of every four American workers&lt;/a&gt;. In the short run, Unemployment Compensation (UC), including the expansions in the CARES Act, will provide a cushion for many people. But this help is time-limited and as people exhaust their UC, the newly unemployed will need to be connected to other benefits including Supplemental Nutrition Assistance Program (SNAP), WIC, health insurance, and other benefits programs that are administered by multiple state agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Millions will be unemployed for the first time and will need help with the basics. Most people won’t know, for example, that they need to apply for UC in one place and apply for food or health insurance benefits through other state agencies. Targeted outreach to people who have been denied or have exhausted UC benefits can connect people with the help they need at the time they need it the most. This play describes how to work with state agencies using a data-driven approach to identify and provide application assistance to individuals who are eligible but not enrolled in SNAP and other benefits programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices-for-this-play&quot;&gt;Best practices for this play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;first-steps-leverage-data-to-identify-people-who-are-likely-eligible-for-help&quot;&gt;First steps: Leverage data to identify people who are likely eligible for help&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Develop data-sharing agreements between agencies to identify people who recently were denied or who exhausted their unemployment benefits and who were not currently enrolled in other benefit programs such as SNAP, WIC, or health insurance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reach out to eligible individuals via direct mail, phone calls, and/or text to make them aware that they may be eligible for other benefits and give them a clear next step such as calling a contact center or accessing an enrollment portal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Help people apply for benefits using the best available resources. This may also require offering help assembling verification documents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;plan-for-sustainability&quot;&gt;Plan for sustainability&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluate results. Ideally this means tracking the number of people contacted, number of responders, number of applications submitted, and number of new enrollments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refresh the data. By continuing to match data on an ongoing basis, state agencies and their partners can continue to identify new individuals who recently exhausted their benefits or were denied eligibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;real-life-example&quot;&gt;Real-life Example&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benefits Data Trust (BDT) partnered with Pennsylvania’s Departments of Public Welfare (DPW; now Human Services) and Labor &amp;amp; Industry in 2010-2014 to conduct targeted outreach to individuals who exhausted or were denied UC benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Over the first three years of the partnership, BDT contacted 253,000 households and screened 48,000 for potential eligibility, resulting in the submission of over 17,000 SNAP applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Almost half of all applicants appeared to qualify for expedited SNAP benefits, indicating they had virtually no income or resources. Those approved received an average benefit of $193 per month.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unemployed Pennsylvanians collectively received about $24 million in SNAP benefits annually, generating nearly $40 million in economic activity each year.
Outreach was paid for with private dollars and federal matching funds, and SNAP benefits are 100% federally funded – so there was virtually no cost to the state.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, contact Alissa Weiss, Director of Partnerships at aweiss@bdtrust.org or 215-779-0467.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clasp.org/blog/helping-unemployed-workers-access-benefits-qa-between-elizabeth-lower-basch-and-rachel-meeks&quot;&gt;Helping Unemployed Workers Access Benefits: A Q&amp;amp;A between Elizabeth Lower-Basch and Rachel Meeks Cahill&lt;/a&gt;, CLASP&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This play was written by Benefits Data Trust, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Manage increased call center volume during COVID-19</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/manage-increased-call-center-volume/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Manage increased call center volume during COVID-19" /><published>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/manage-increased-call-center-volume</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/manage-increased-call-center-volume/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;This play was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://mrelief.com/&quot;&gt;mRelief&lt;/a&gt;, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For community-based organizations and government agencies that operate a call center, the number of incoming calls from clients has increased dramatically. Managing a high number of calls from clients with urgent needs is very challenging and can place a strain on call center employees. As clients call with questions about eligibility requirements, application options, interview schedule, case status, renewal options and benefit amount, triaging calls can be very difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article includes a few recommendations on managing the number of incoming calls while still meeting clients’ needs, ensuring that questions are answered as efficiently as possible and supporting the needs of call center staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices-for-this-play&quot;&gt;Best practices for this play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-can-be-done-quickly&quot;&gt;What can be done quickly&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Help clients understand the program requirements before they call&lt;/strong&gt; - Clearly sharing program requirements or providing an eligibility pre-screener next to the call center number can help answer questions before the client calls. When clients have easy access to program information, they can begin the application process without calling to ask questions about eligibility. In one implementation with a community-based organization in Chicago, adding a pre-screener next to the hotline on the website reduced calls by 57% in a month and directed clients quickly to the information they need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set up call back options&lt;/strong&gt; - As an increase in the number of calls can increase hold-times, setting up the option to request a callback can help clients minimize the time they spend enrolling in social services. When clients have not had to wait on hold, they are less likely to express frustration to call center staff.  Given that some clients have limited phone plans, a call back option can save critical phone minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share information and set expectations on the recording&lt;/strong&gt; - In addition to setting up a callback option, communicating the amount of time that a client can expect to wait on hold helps people plan accordingly. When possible, sharing information about available online resources can help clients understand all of their options while waiting on hold.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Track the number of incoming calls&lt;/strong&gt; - Understanding the call volume and how it fluctuates based on the day of the week or the time of day in the short-term can be a critical foundation for making longer-term changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-to-aim-for-long-term&quot;&gt;What to aim for long term&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set up scheduling options&lt;/strong&gt; - Creating an online scheduling system for people to set up a time to speak with someone at the call center can reduce repeat calls and manage call flow through the day.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow up over text messaging&lt;/strong&gt; - Sending any critical follow-up over text messaging such as websites, applications, documents needed or phone numbers can reduce the need for people to call as a follow-up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mrelief.com/blog/announcement_from_catholic_charities&quot;&gt;Partnership with Catholic Charities&lt;/a&gt;, mRelief&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeforamerica.org/news/covid-19s-impact-on-the-social-safety-net&quot;&gt;COVID-19’s Impact on the Social Safety Net&lt;/a&gt;, Code for America&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This play was written by mRelief, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Stand up a new system rapidly to get benefits to families (Pandemic-EBT)</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/pandemic-ebt/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Stand up a new system rapidly to get benefits to families (Pandemic-EBT)" /><published>2020-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/pandemic-ebt</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/pandemic-ebt/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;This play was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://codeforamerica.org/&quot;&gt;Code for America&lt;/a&gt;, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to the COVID-19 pandemic, Congress has authorized states to make unprecedented changes to safety net programs like SNAP through the Families First and CARES Acts. While these new policy authorizations are important for states to be able to move quickly to serve people in need, it’s not easy to make changes to statewide eligibility systems on a dime. And it’s a profound challenge to devise and implement an entirely new statewide benefit that didn’t exist before, as is the case with Pandemic EBT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fns.usda.gov/snap/state-guidance-coronavirus-pandemic-ebt-pebt&quot;&gt;Pandemic EBT (P-EBT)&lt;/a&gt; is a federal initiative to provide students that receive free and reduced price (FRP) school meals with a replacement food benefit to pay for groceries while schools are physically closed. The idea is simple and important - find families whose kids are eligible for FRP school meals and issue them EBT benefits. But the implementation is far more complicated. In many cases, data that lets states know who is eligible to receive P-EBT benefits is spread across multiple sources. This means that launching the benefit requires data sharing between state agencies - perhaps even creating new data transfer pathways between school districts, state education departments, and social services agencies - that didn’t exist before. In some cases, states are hustling to launch new digital applications for P-EBT in just weeks. Standing up a new P-EBT benefit surfaces numerous technical, logistical, and communication challenges, and the implementation of Pandemic EBT raises some important best practices for how governments can move quickly and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeforamerica.org/safetynetblueprint/principles/responsive-to-changing-needs/&quot;&gt;respond to changing needs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices-for-this-play&quot;&gt;Best practices for this play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-can-be-done-quickly&quot;&gt;What can be done quickly&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use existing data where possible.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Always use information you already have about people first, before asking them for new information. In the case of P-EBT, children in households that receive SNAP, TANF, and other means-tested social services automatically qualify for free school meals. Existing state data can therefore be used to identify students who are categorically eligible for free school meals and P-EBT, and to issue that benefit directly to them. Some states maintain current state-level data on FRP-eligible children, and have been able to utilize that data for direct issuance of P-EBT to all eligible children without the need for new information or an application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborate effectively across agencies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In order to implement P-EBT, state agencies need to collect or validate FRP data that is housed at the school district level. Collecting, consolidating, and matching this data takes quick cooperation between the social services agency, the department of education, and all the individual school districts. Agencies need to work together to rapidly establish a system for sharing data across all of these agencies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use off-the-shelf tools or other fast, simple technology to fill in the gaps.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In some cases there still may be people eligible for the new benefit that cannot be found within existing data. In this case it’s possible to quickly stand up a new form or online application to capture these people’s information. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeforamerica.org/news/code-for-america-and-u-s-digital-response-partner-to-help-states-reach-families-with-pandemic-ebt&quot;&gt;Code for America has built an online application for P-EBT&lt;/a&gt; that is &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/codeforamerica/pandemic-ebt&quot;&gt;open-source&lt;/a&gt;, which any state can use. States or local agencies can also look to leverage existing text message platforms, social media, robocall systems, or other off-the-shelf technology to communicate with eligible families who may be hard to reach by mail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-to-aim-for-long-term&quot;&gt;What to aim for long term&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preemtively build communication pathways between agencies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Make sure that pathways for sharing data between systems and agencies are set up and agreed upon ahead of time. It’s safe to assume that all states will face future emergencies or natural disasters where a quick response is needed. Establish pathways and protocols for sharing data between agencies, so that when data is needed quickly, it’s easy to transfer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Establish systems for data standardization.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Using data effectively for the issuance of new benefits is complicated when data is inconsistent across agencies, or key pieces of information are missing or out of date. Standardizing data across agencies will make it easier to combine and compare. For instance, do all school districts capture the same information from families, or does that data vary district to district? It will also be helpful to establish consistent procedures for keeping information you have on file up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Employ digital outreach strategies to reach people at scale.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Digital marketing strategies and best practices should be a key element of outreach, particularly during times of crisis or with new or unfamiliar services or benefits. Serving people requires finding ways to effectively reach them where they are. There are popular assumptions that vulnerable populations can’t be reached online - but that’s no longer the case. Code for America’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/codeforamerica-cms1/documents/CfA-Digital-Outreach-Playbook-2018.pdf&quot;&gt;Digital Outreach Playbook&lt;/a&gt; provides principles and best practices for digital outreach to vulnerable or hard-to-reach populations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeforamerica.org/safetynetblueprint/&quot;&gt;Blueprint for a Human-Centered Safety Net&lt;/a&gt; - Code for America&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeforamerica.org/news/delivery-driven-policy&quot;&gt;Delivery-Driven Policy: Policy Designed for the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt; - Code for America&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/codeforamerica-cms1/documents/CfA-Digital-Outreach-Playbook-2018.pdf&quot;&gt;Digital Outreach Playbook&lt;/a&gt; - Code for America&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alluma.org/improving-customer-service-health-and-human-services-through-technology&quot;&gt;Improving Customer Service in Health and Human Services Through Technology - Part 4&lt;/a&gt; - Alluma&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alluma.org/maximizing-linkages-policymakers-guide-data-sharing&quot;&gt;Maximizing Linkages: A Policymaker’s Guide to Data-Sharing&lt;/a&gt; - Alluma&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This play was written by Code for America, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Design simple and effective forms for benefit programs</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/design-simple-and-effective-forms-for-benefit-programs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Design simple and effective forms for benefit programs" /><published>2020-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/design-simple-and-effective-forms-for-benefit-programs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/design-simple-and-effective-forms-for-benefit-programs/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;This play was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://civilla.com/&quot;&gt;Civilla&lt;/a&gt;, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people are turning to federal, state, and local benefit programs to support their families during the COVID-19 pandemic. Benefit forms that don’t account for the needs of clients can jeopardize their ability to quickly receive and maintain the benefits they’re eligible for. When faced with confusing requirements, difficult-to-follow directions, and unclear next steps, clients often make errors or fail to submit the required documentation. Here are best practices for designing simple and effective forms – whether it’s online or through fillable PDFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices-for-this-play&quot;&gt;Best practices for this play&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, agencies should use three primary design directives to guide their form design:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Short&lt;/strong&gt;. Forms should collect what is necessary and no more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple&lt;/strong&gt;. Design and copy should be clear and easy to understand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevant&lt;/strong&gt;. Only ask for information necessary to the programs that clients are applying for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-can-be-done-quickly&quot;&gt;What can be done quickly&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use plain language.&lt;/strong&gt; Update policy and legal language on forms to ensure it’s easy for clients to understand. Write like you’re talking to clients one-on-one, but with the authority of a frontline staff member who can actively help.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trim the excess.&lt;/strong&gt; Respect the gravity of the situation clients are in by stripping out all language, questions, and requirements that aren’t absolutely necessary. Include only what someone needs to know so they can complete their task.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Write for a universal audience.&lt;/strong&gt; Improve readability by choosing words carefully and user testing forms to ensure that they resonate with a wide audience – including people with low literacy and language barriers – while respecting people’s abilities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design forms with clear hierarchy and scale.&lt;/strong&gt; Increase the hierarchy between page titles, section headers, and body text to help clients read efficiently and focus on what’s most important.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Group questions around key themes.&lt;/strong&gt; Organize pages around a single topic (ex: Household Members, Assets, Income, Expenses) to allow clients to focus on one part of their life at a time. Group similar information together to improve clarity and flow – enabling clients to orient to each section and contextualize questions within it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Focus on a single call to action and simple steps.&lt;/strong&gt; Focus forms on a single call to action. Include simple steps (10 words or less) to help clients understand what they need to do next.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid paragraphs.&lt;/strong&gt; Break up large blocks of text. Utilize lists with numbers and simple bullets.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use tool tips.&lt;/strong&gt; Include tool tips to answer common client questions and clarify complex information that may be required due to policy and legal requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid capitalization.&lt;/strong&gt; DO NOT USE BLOCK CAPITALS FOR TEXT. It makes it sounds like you’re shouting and it’s hard to read. Unless mandated by law, consider other type treatments for uppercase text.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update the typeface.&lt;/strong&gt; Choose a sans-serif font that is clear, warm, and easy to read. Some open-source typefaces to consider using include: Source Sans Pro, Public Sans, and Roboto Mono.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increase whitespace.&lt;/strong&gt; Update forms to provide as much whitespace as possible. Use less whitespace to group elements and more whitespace to distinguish them from each other.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide confirmation and next steps.&lt;/strong&gt; Include details that give clients confidence and set expectations for what comes next.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-to-aim-for-long-term&quot;&gt;What to aim for long term&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design integrated and streamlined applications and renewals.&lt;/strong&gt; Integrate benefit programs into a single, streamlined application and renewal to ensure residents only fill out information that is relevant to their case. Separate information into a core form (with information that is required for all or most clients to complete) and program supplements (information that is program-specific and tailored to each client’s case).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design a proofs page.&lt;/strong&gt; Create a guide that provides plain-language examples of the documents clients may need to submit to include with their application and renewals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design an information booklet.&lt;/strong&gt; Create a dedicated space for required policy and legal information that isn’t needed directly on forms. This provides clients with a portable resource to reference online or take home with them when they have finished completing their task.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Design a standardized interview guide.&lt;/strong&gt; Create a standardized interview guide that is paired with applications and renewals to ensure that all federal, state, and departmental policies are covered. This will provide a helpful tool for caseworkers and create a more consistent experience for clients.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Include pre-fill information.&lt;/strong&gt; Where possible, pre-fill information from the client’s case file to give them a head-start on completing their forms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://plainlanguage.gov/guidelines/&quot;&gt;Federal plain language guidelines&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://designsystem.digital.gov/&quot;&gt;U.S. Web Design System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5d05998888b6c9000122325d/t/5e28d0e7443f762e375435bc/1579733237605/MDHHS-1171-StyleGuide-Civilla-1.17.pdf&quot;&gt;Application style guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5d05998888b6c9000122325d/t/5de978d72fe4683bc4aaee60/1575581928117/Civilla+Project+ReNew+Report.pdf&quot;&gt;Designing simple and intuitive renewals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1Tt2lmxPUPlj7MWWgwBAU8ErE_2LFNtet0YOQHgnkK74/edit#slide=id.g3592adab5a_0_160&quot;&gt;Design Patterns from the digital assister in Michigan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.navapbc.com/toolkits/conduct-user-research-to-improve-forms.html&quot;&gt;Conduct user research to improve forms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/content-design/writing-for-gov-uk#plain-english&quot;&gt;Content design: planning, writing, and managing content&lt;/a&gt; (Gov.uk)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://oes.gsa.gov/assets/abstracts/OES%20Learnings%20on%20Writing%20Better%20Communications%202018.pdf&quot;&gt;How to design effective communications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This play was written by Civilla, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Serve clients online</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/serve-clients-online/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Serve clients online" /><published>2020-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/serve-clients-online</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/serve-clients-online/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;This play was written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://singlestop.org/&quot;&gt;Single Stop&lt;/a&gt;, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you moved the work your organization usually does in-person online? Are you meeting with your clients over video conference platforms? This play focuses on tips and tricks for successfully working with your clients one-on-one virtually to deliver the supports and services you usually provide in person. Touching on areas such as choosing the right tools to use, addressing common client challenges with technology, rapport-building, sharing information and resources, and maintaining client privacy, this play is designed to support any professional holding meetings with clients online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices-for-this-play&quot;&gt;Best practices for this play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;preparation&quot;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select an appropriate platform to use consistently with clients. Whenever possible use the same platform every time you meet with a client.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communicate to current and new clients that meetings will occur online.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Provide clients with clear instructions on how to access the platform along with the basics on how to use it successfully. &lt;strong&gt;Remember that many clients may not be tech-savvy and will need additional help&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare yourself and your team to teach the use of the tool when meeting with clients.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan for a backup in case the platform does not work or the client does not have internet access.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Prepare your space to create a comfortable and distraction-free environment for the client.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open any websites, documents, or other visuals you might use in your browser in advance of the session.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ensure you are prepared to address accessibility issues. Zoom offers closed captioning, for example, to better support deaf and hard of hearing clients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;during-the-meeting&quot;&gt;During the meeting&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build rapport as closely to the same way you do in-person. Your tone and body language are useful things to communicate comfort and safety to a client. For sighted clients, place your camera where you can make it appear you are looking them in the eye.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Utilize the same listening and communication techniques you would use in your in-person meetings. Reflective listening, motivational interviewing, and other techniques are no different over video. This helps clients you used to meet with in person feel like the only thing that has changed is the venue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Screen share the notes you are taking or the form you are filling out (if applicable) to show the client you are understanding what they are saying. This can increase trust and allows the client to correct any reflections or thoughts you might be taking down.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Screen share any forms you are helping the client complete.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allow the client to record the meeting if that is helpful to them, or record it and send the recording afterward.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schedule any follow-ups with the client before you sign off. Confirm they got any meeting invites you send. &lt;strong&gt;Turn off screen sharing before you open your calendar to protect the privacy of other clients&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;regarding-privacy&quot;&gt;Regarding privacy&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Show client know your conversation is private, use your camera to give a quick span of the space to show them no one is listening off-camera.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you require consent for any portion of the meeting you can use a record function to get it verbally, or you could use a platform such as DocuSign to obtain consent. Online survey tools could also be used if it is made clear that by submitting the answers to the survey are an indication of consent.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Close out any items related to other clients before screen sharing to ensure you don’t show someone else’s information accidentally.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encrypt emails sent to a client that include any forms, recordings, documents, or other items.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For more information on, see our play &lt;a href=&quot;../make-remote-work&quot;&gt;using technology to make the transition from in-person to remote assistance easier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This play was written by Single Stop, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Use technology to make the transition from in-person to remote assistance easier</title><link href="https://socialtech.us/playbook/make-remote-work/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Use technology to make the transition from in-person to remote assistance easier" /><published>2020-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://socialtech.us/playbook/make-remote-work</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://socialtech.us/playbook/make-remote-work/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;This play was written by &lt;a href=&quot;alluma.org&quot;&gt;Alluma&lt;/a&gt;, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the COVID-19 emergency, many agencies administering social services programs were already adopting remote options to apply and enroll so that clients did not need to visit an office to do everything. During the COVID-19 emergency, it’s simply not possible to conduct business as usual if staff and clients are to be kept safe. Agencies need to make it possible for clients to do anything and everything needed to access programs without visiting an office. Policies for many of the programs people are relying on for basic needs are changing rapidly to make remote assistance possible, and these are only part of the effort needed to transition to completely remote assistance. This play provides guidance to agencies on how to use technology in ways to make this rapid transition smoother and more successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;best-practices-for-this-play&quot;&gt;Best practices for this play&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-can-be-done-quickly&quot;&gt;What can be done quickly&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are good practices that can potentially be done easily and quickly by your agency, depending on what tools the agency is already equipped with today. If your agency cannot do these easily or quickly, then aim to do them in the long-term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow all assistance, appointments, and interviews to be done remotely.&lt;/strong&gt; If any are required, also consider waiving those requirements, at least temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Set clients up for success by sending them information and reminders.&lt;/strong&gt; Ideas for how to do this include:
Let clients know about their options to apply, maintain, and renew benefits or services (such as through an online portal, over the phone, etc.). Include instructions on how to use them.
Provide clients an easy-to-understand checklist of which documents count for different eligibility requirements. Explain what to do if a client does not have a needed document.
Send clients reminders about upcoming things they need to do, such as appointments, interviews, or renewal deadlines.
Send appointment and interview details in advance, including what clients may need to bring and be prepared to talk about.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Give clients more control over their time.&lt;/strong&gt; Ways to do this include:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If using an instant messaging platform, ensure that response times are much shorter than they may be for phone calls. Individuals are prepared to wait on hold when they reach a call center, but expect an immediate response to an instant message.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For appointments and interviews, allow on-demand scheduling. This can be done via online portals, text messaging, etc. to schedule, reschedule, or cancel.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Notify callers of expected wait times, and offer an option for the agency to call the client back instead of keeping the client on the phone.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reassure clients.&lt;/strong&gt; Ways to do this include:
If making outbound calls to clients, work with phone companies to be sure your agency name appears on the caller ID, rather than an unfamiliar number clients may not answer.
After an action is completed (e.g. an application is submitted or a document uploaded), provide the client with a confirmation on the screen and/or by email.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-to-aim-for-long-term&quot;&gt;What to aim for long-term&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are things your agency can do that may involve more effort and time to implement. They are worth the investment, however, as they will help your agency’s clients far beyond just this current crisis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cultivate more communication channels that clients can use for applying, maintaining, and renewing their access to benefits or services.&lt;/strong&gt; Examples to explore are text messaging, instant messaging platforms, chatbots, interactive voice response (IVR) phone systems, and online portals.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To get the most out of your new communication channels, consider making these policy and technology updates too:&lt;/strong&gt;
Accept alternative forms of collecting signatures (e.g. electronic or telephonic signatures) for applications and renewals.
Allow multiple ways to submit documentation. Allow clients to take photos of documents through their mobile devices, and then submit them through online portals, text messages, instant messaging platforms, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expand functionality of online portals to enable clients to do more things themselves.&lt;/strong&gt; Obvious functionality to add include ways for clients to report changes and check benefits or services statuses themselves. But there may be additional ideas that your agency’s clients would appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;a-few-more-points-to-consider&quot;&gt;A few more points to consider&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Take a “mobile first” approach to online options. Design first and foremost for mobile devices because, for many people, their phone is the primary or only way to access the internet. You can’t assume that everyone has a computer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make sure that an online service works on all available browsers (for example, Chrome, Firefox, Safari).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Remind staff and clients to either delete personal information used on a mobile device (including tablets) if it is a shared device or to enable the device’s security features.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;See our play on &lt;a href=&quot;../play-1&quot;&gt;text messaging&lt;/a&gt; best practices for further tips.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alluma.org/decoding-common-challenges-leveraging-low-tech-fixes-better-customer-service&quot;&gt;Decoding Common Challenges &amp;amp; Leveraging Low-tech Fixes for Better Customer Service&lt;/a&gt;, Alluma&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alluma.org/improving-customer-service-health-and-human-services-through-technology&quot;&gt;Improving Customer Service in Health and Human Services Through Technology&lt;/a&gt;, Alluma&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bdtrust.org/benefits-access-in-a-pandemic-helping-people-from-the-safety-of-their-homes/&quot;&gt;Benefits access in a pandemic: Helping people from the safety of their homes&lt;/a&gt;, Benefits Data Trust&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.civilla.com/modernizing-online-enrollment&quot;&gt;Modernizing online enrollment for Michigan’s largest assistance programs&lt;/a&gt;, Civilla&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeforamerica.org/news/covid-19s-impact-on-the-social-safety-net&quot;&gt;COVID-19’s Impact on the Social Safety Net&lt;/a&gt;, Code for America&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.codeforamerica.org/news/the-missed-opportunity-in-online-benefits-applications-mobile-first&quot;&gt;The Missed Opportunity in Online Benefits Applications: Mobile First&lt;/a&gt;, Code for America&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This play was written by Alluma, one of the partners in the Social Tech Collaborative.</summary></entry></feed>